The AlloSphere: it's a three-story metal sphere
آلوإسفير. أنها قصة مخروط معدني من ثلاث طبقات
in an echo-free chamber.
في غرفة خالية من الصدى.
Think of the AlloSphere as a large,
فكّر في ألوسفير (AlloSphere) كمنظار رقمي ،
dynamically varying digital microscope
ضخم متغير دايناميكيا
that's connected to a supercomputer.
موصول بحاسوب عملاق.
20 researchers can stand on a bridge
يستطيع عشرون باحثاً الوقوف في الجسر
suspended inside of the sphere, and be
معلقين داخل المخروط، ويكونوا مغمورين تماماً
completely immersed in their data.
في بياناتهم.
Imagine if a team of physicists
تخيل أن بمستطاع فريق من
could stand inside of an atom
الفيزيائيين الوقوف داخل ذرّة
and watch and hear electrons spin.
ويسمعون ويشاهدون دوران الإلكترون.
Imagine if a group of sculptors
تخيّل لو بإمكان مجموعة من النحاتين
could be inside of a lattice of atoms
الدخول في شبكة من الذرّات
and sculpt with their material.
والنحت بإستخدام موادهم.
Imagine if a team of surgeons could fly
تخيّل لو بإمكان فريق من الجراحين التحليق
into the brain, as though it was a world,
داخل الدماغ، كما لو كان ذلك في العالم،
and see tissues as landscapes,
ويروا الأنسجة كالمناظر الطبيعية،
and hear blood density levels as music.
ويسمعون مستويات كثافة الدم كالموسيقى.
This is some of the research that you're going to see
هذه بعض البحوث التي سنراها
that we're undertaking at the AlloSphere.
والتي تعهدنا بها في ألوسفير.
But first a little bit about this group
لكن بداية خلفية قليلة عن هذه المجموعة
of artists, scientists, and engineers
من الفنانين، العلماء، المهندسين،
that are working together.
الذين يعملون سوياً.
I'm a composer, orchestrally-trained,
أنا مؤلف، متدرب على الأوركسترا،
and the inventor of the AlloSphere.
ومبتكر الآلوإسفير.
With my visual artist colleagues, we map
مع زملائي الفنانين التشكيليين، نجسّد
complex mathematical algorithms that unfold in time and space,
خوارزميات رياضية معقدة لا تظهر في الزمان والفراغ،
visually and sonically.
بصرياً وصوتياً.
Our scientist colleagues are finding new patterns
زملاؤنا العلماء يجدون أنماط جديدة
in the information.
في المعلومات.
And our engineering colleagues are making
وزملاؤنا المهندسين يصنعون أحد أكبر
one of the largest dynamically varying computers in the world
الحواسيب المتغيرة دايناميكيا في العالم
for this kind of data exploration.
لهذا النوع من إستكشاف البيانات.
I'm going to fly you into five research projects
سأقوم بجولة حول خمس مشاريع بحثية
in the AlloSphere that are going to take you from
في الألوسفير التي تطوف بكم من
biological macroscopic data
البيانات الحيوية المجهرية
all the way down to electron spin.
طوال الطريق حتى دوران الإلكترون.
This first project is called the AlloBrain.
هذا المشروع الأول يسمى ألوبرين. (AlloBrain)
And it's our attempt to quantify beauty
وهو محاولتنا لقياس الجمال
by finding which regions of the brain
بمعرفة أي أجزاء من الدماغ
are interactive while witnessing something beautiful.
تتفاعل عندما نشاهد شيئاً جميلاً.
You're flying through the cortex of my colleague's brain.
أنتم تحلقون عبر قشرة زميلي الدماغية.
Our narrative here is real fMRI data
ترجمتنا هنا هي بيانات للرنين المغناطيسي الوظيفي الحقيقية
that's mapped visually and sonically.
التي تجسّدت بصرياً وسمعياً.
The brain now a world that we can fly through and interact with.
الدماغ الآن هو عالم يمكن التحليق عبره والتفاعل معه.
You see 12 intelligent computer agents,
تشاهدون 12 وكيلاً لحواسيب ذكية،
the little rectangles that are flying in the brain with you.
المثلثات الصغيرة التي تحلّق معكم في الدماغ.
They're mining blood density levels.
أنها تنقّب مستوى كثافة الدم.
And they're reporting them back to you sonically.
وتقوم بإرسال تقرير لكم صوتياً.
Higher density levels mean
مستويات كثافة عالية تعني
more activity in that point of the brain.
نشاط أكثر من وجهة نظر الدماغ.
They're actually singing these densities to you
في الواقع أنهم يغنون هذه الكثافات لكم
with higher pitches mapped to higher densities.
مع درجات موسيقية مرتفعة مجسّدة للكثافات الأعلى.
We're now going to move from real biological data
سنغادر الآن من البيانات الإحيائية الحقيقية
to biogenerative algorithms that create artificial nature
الى خوارزميات التوليد الحيوي التي تخلق طبيعة مصطنعة
in our next artistic and scientific installation.
في تنصيبنا الفني والعلمي القادم.
In this artistic and scientific installation, biogenerative algorithms
في هذا التنصيب الفني والعلمي، خوارزميات التوليد الحيوي
are helping us to understand
تساعدنا في فهم
self-generation and growth:
التوالد الذاتي والنمو.
very important for simulation in the nanoscaled sciences.
مهم جداً للمحاكاة في علوم حجم النانو.
For artists, we're making new worlds
بالنسبة للفنانين، نصنع عوالم جديدة
that we can uncover and explore.
تمكنك من الكشف والإستكشاف.
These generative algorithms grow over time,
و خوارزميات التوليد هذه تنمو بمرور الوقت،
and they interact and communicate as a swarm of insects.
إنها تتفاعل وتتواصل كسرب من الحشرات.
Our researchers are interacting with this data
باحثونا يتفاعلون مع هذه البيانات
by injecting bacterial code,
بحقن شفرة بكتيرية،
which are computer programs,
التي هي برمجيات حواسيب،
that allow these creatures to grow over time.
و التي تتيح لهذه المخلوقات بالنمو مع مرور الوقت.
We're going to move now from the biological
سنقوم بالمغادرة الآن من عوالم
and the macroscopic world,
الأحياء والمايكروسكوب،
down into the atomic world,
أسفل الى العالم الذري،
as we fly into a lattice of atoms.
كما نحلق في شبكة من الذرات.
This is real AFM -- Atomic Force Microscope -- data
هذه بيانات حقيقية لـ(AFM) قوى الذرة المايكروسكوبية،
from my colleagues in the Solid State Lighting and Energy Center.
من زميلي في مركز إضاءة الجمادات والطاقة.
They've discovered a new bond,
لقد اكتشفوا رابط جديد،
a new material for transparent solar cells.
مادة جديدة لخلايا الطاقة الشمسية الشفافة.
We're flying through 2,000 lattice of atoms --
نحن نحلق عبر 2000 شبكة من الذرات --
oxygen, hydrogen and zinc.
أوكسجين، هايدروجين وزنك.
You view the bond in the triangle.
تشاهدون الرابط في المثلث.
It's four blue zinc atoms
إنها أربعة ذرات زنك زرقاء
bonding with one white hydrogen atom.
مرتبطة بذرة هايدروجين أبيض.
You see the electron flow with the streamlines
تشاهدون تدفق الإلكترون مع خطوط الإنسياب
we as artists have generated for the scientists.
و التي أنتجناها نحن كفنانين من أجل العلماء.
This is allowing them to find the bonding nodes in any lattice of atoms.
يسمح لهم هذا بالعثور على العقد الروابط في أي شبكة ذرات.
We think it makes a beautiful structural art.
نعتقد نحن بأن هذا يشكل هيكلا فنيا جميلا.
The sound that you're hearing are the actual
الصوت الذي تسمعونه حقيقي
emission spectrums of these atoms.
و هو عبارة عن أطياف الانبعاثات لهذه الذرات.
We've mapped them into the audio domain,
جسدّناها الى مجال للصوت.
so they're singing to you.
اذاً فأنهم يغنون لكم.
Oxygen, hydrogen and zinc have their own signature.
لدى ذرات الأوكسجين، و الهايدروجين والزنك بصماتها الخاصة.
We're going to actually move even further down
سنقوم بالمغادرة الى أسفل أكثر
as we go from this lattice of atoms
بينما تذهبون من هذه الشبكة من الذرات
to one single hydrogen atom.
إلى ذرة هايدروجين واحدة.
We're working with our physicist colleagues
نعمل مع زملائنا الفيزيائيين
that have given us the mathematical calculations
الذين قدموا لنا الحسابات الرياضية
of the n-dimensional Schrödinger equation in time.
للوقت الذي فيه تعتمد على معادلة شرودنغر ثلاثية الأبعاد.
What you're seeing here right now is a superposition of an electron
ما ترونه هنا الآن هو تراكب الالكترون
in the lower three orbitals of a hydrogen atom.
في المدارات الثلاث الأدنى لذرة الهايدروجين
You're actually hearing and seeing the electron flow with the lines.
في الواقع أنكم تسمعون وتشاهدون سريان الإلكترون مع الخطوط.
The white dots are the probability wave
النقاط البيضاء هي موجة إحتمالية
that will show you where the electron is
التي ستبين لكم أين هو الإلكترون
in any given point of time and space
في أي نقطة معطى للزمن والفراغ
in this particular three-orbital configuration.
في هذا التكوين الخاص للمدارات الثلاث
In a minute we're going to move to a two-orbital configuration,
في دقيقة سنقوم بالمغادرة الى تكوينات مدارين.
and you're going to notice a pulsing.
وستلاحظون وجود نبض.
And you're going to hear an undulation between the sound.
وستسمعون تموّج بين الصوت.
This is actually a light emitter.
هذا في الواقع باعث الضوء.
As the sound starts to pulse and contract,
وبينما يبدأ الصوت في النبض والإنقباض،
our physicists can tell when a photon is going to be emitted.
يمكن لعلماء الفيزياء لدينا تحديد متى سيشع الفوتون.
They're starting to find new mathematical structures
لقد بدأوا في إيجاد أسس رياضية جديدة
in these calculations.
في حساباتهم.
And they're understanding more about quantum mathematics.
ويفهمون أكثر حول الرياضيات الكمّية.
We're going to move even further down,
سنقوم بالمغادرة الى أسفل أكثر،
and go to one single electron spin.
ونذهب لدوران إلكترون واحد.
This will be the final project that I show you.
سيكون هذا آخر مشروع أعرضه لكم.
Our colleagues in the Center for Quantum Computation
زملاؤنا في مركز حسابات الكمّ
and Spintronics are actually measuring with their lasers
والإلكترونيات المحورية، يعملون بقياس الليزر في الواقع
decoherence in a single electron spin.
عدم التماسك على مستوى محور إلكترون واحد.
We've taken this information and we've
أخذنا هذه المعلومات وقمنا
made a mathematical model out of it.
بعمل نموذج رياضي لنجسده منه.
You're actually seeing and hearing
تسمعون وتشاهدون في الواقع
quantum information flow.
كمّية إنسياب المعلومات
This is very important for the next step in simulating
هذا مهم جداً للخطوة القادمة في محاكاة
quantum computers and information technology.
الحاسوب الكمّي وتكنولوجيا المعلومات.
So these brief examples that I've shown you
وهذه أمثلة مقتضبة عرضتها عليكم
give you an idea of the kind of work that we're doing
لإعطاءكم فكرة لهذا النوع من العمل الذي نقوم به
at the University of California, Santa Barbara,
في جامعة كاليفورنيا، سانتا باربارا،
to bring together, arts, science
لنجمع سوياً، الفنون، العلوم،
and engineering
والهندسة،
into a new age of math, science and art.
في حقبة جديدة من الرياضيات، و العلوم، والفنون.
We hope that all of you will come to see the AlloSphere.
نأمل أن تأتوا جميعاً لرؤية ألوسفير.
Inspire us to think of new ways that we can use
وتلهمونا للتفكير بطرق جديدة يمكن أن نستخدمها
this unique instrument that we've created at Santa Barbara.
هذا الجهاز المتفرد الذي صنعناه في سانتا باربارا
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)